I want you to go back to China and
you're going to take with you a bedroom
set that I give you and the dresser is
going to have a transmitting device
embedded in the back of it. I've already
identified your vulnerability. Maybe
your kid is sick and needs medical
treatment in the United States. So,
you're not an idiot. You know what's
happening here. And so, you do it very
gently. And I say, "Dalton, listen. You
know how I feel about you. You're my
best friend. I love you. I love your
wife. Our kids are friends. We're going
to be friends forever. But I haven't
been 100% honest with you and I hope
you're not going to be upset.
>> Let's say you recruit me as an asset. I
work in, you know, the Iranian embassy
somewhere and you meet me at a cocktail
party and I say, "Oh, John, this this
guy is he's he's a wonderful guy. I'm
going to get to know him a little bit."
>> Yeah.
>> And we become best friends, as you say,
over 6, nine months, whatever the period
is. Yep.
>> And you pitched me one day.
>> Mhm.
>> And
what I'm getting at is what is the
psychological process that an asset goes
through? Like what kind of crisis goes
on as this happens?
Yeah, that's a great question.
There's a there's a little dance that's
happening here. I I asked one of my
instructors when I first went into the
operational training, what percentage of
people that you have pitched in your
career said yes. He said 100. 100%. He
said, 'If you are not 100% certain that
this guy's going to say yes, run for the
hills because he's going to out you,
you're going to get arrested, you're
going to get expelled from the country,
he's going to report you to his own
intelligence service, and then you're
not going to be able to travel to half
the countries in the world. That
happened to a colleague of mine where,
you know, we we all read each other's
cables and we're like, "Dude, keep up
the good work, man. You're going to get
them. next meeting you're going to get
him right. So I'm reading my colleagues
cables and it's it couldn't be going any
better and he asks headquarters
permission. You have to get permission
to make the actual pitch.
It's very paperworkheavy.
So headquarters says go for it. Go with
God. And he makes the pitch. And the guy
literally runs screaming from the room
and next thing you know his ambassador
calls our ambassador and his government
lodges a formal diplomatic complaint
with our government. What are you going
to do? You're going to say, "Yeah, my
guy's an undercover CIA guy." So, you
can't say that. So, you say, "No, no,
no, no, no. This is just a
misunderstanding. It was a language
thing. Our guy doesn't really speak your
language very well and your guy doesn't
speak English very well. This was just
an innocent misunderstanding, but we
understand if you're upset, so we're
going to instruct our guy not to ever
talk to your guy again.
That's uncomfortable.
Besides the fact that you look like an
idiot at headquarters because you've
been telling us for nine months how well
things are going and in fact the guy
never had any intention of allowing you
to recruit him. Like, what have you been
doing all this time?
You're supposed to be whining him and
dining him and showing him the better,
finer things in life so that he says,
"Hey, you know, I'm kind of liking I
make $500 a month. This guy's ordering
$200 bottles of wine and he paid for us
to go on vacation and he bought me a
Rolex. I'm going to say yes to this."
And in fact, he says, "Not just no," but
oh, hell no.
So,
what you're looking for is a
vulnerability. This is this is a very
important word in the what's called the
the asset acquisition cycle. The asset
acquisition cycle is spot, assess,
develop, recruit. I spot you at a
diplomatic cocktail party. I assess that
you have access to information that I
that I want. I develop you by creating
this friendship and then I recruit you.
Now, by the time I recruit you, you know
exactly what's going on. You're not an
idiot.
And why am I spending all this money on
you? You know, where am I getting all
this money? Rolexes and, you know, fancy
vacations and
what's up? So, you're not an idiot. You
know what's happening here.
And so, you do it very gently. And I
say, "Dalton, listen. You know how I
feel about you. You're my best friend.
I love you. I love your wife. My wife
loves you. My wife loves your wife. Our
kids are friends. We're going to be
friends forever. But I haven't been 100%
honest with you. And I hope you're not
going to be upset. But I'm actually a
CIA officer undercover. That's called
breaking cover. And I I hope you're okay
with that.
I know you're going to be okay with that
because you know exactly where this is
going. I've already identified your
vulnerability. Maybe your kid is sick
and needs medical treatment in the
United States. Maybe your kid wants to
go to school in the United States. I can
get your kid accepted to literally any
university in America and I'll pay for
it. any university in America
100% paid so long as you keep giving me
and my you know colleagues who replace
me and replace each other what they ask
for.
Um
so I take you off to the side and I say
listen just for your protection
we can't be seen as friends anymore. our
relationship has to become clandestine
from this point on.
>> And so we're gonna meet once a month at
a predetermined site at a predetermined
time and date and then we'll carry on
from there. Now, if you're from an enemy
country, I don't want you to defect.
That's the last thing I want because if
you defect, your value ends today
because you lose your access. Well, I
don't care what was happening yesterday.
I want to know what your country's going
to do tomorrow. Right? So, the goal is
let's say you and I are stationed in uh
you know, Bogotaa.
I want you to go back to Iran or Russia
or China
or Cuba
and you're going to take with you
a bedroom
a bedroom set that I give you, right?
And the dresser
is going to have a
a transmitting device embedded in the
back of it. And so
you're going to type your reports onto a
chip. You put the chip in the device.
You hit a button that's hidden in the
back of the drawer and it does a burst
transmission that lasts about a half of
a second or a tenth of a second and it's
going to send your report back to CIA
headquarters. And because the burst only
lasts for a tenth of a second, nobody's
going to be able to intercept it.
They're going to say, "Oh, there was
just a transmission. It lasted a tenth
of a second. We have no idea where it
came from."
Because once you get back to Iran or
Cuba or Russia or China or whatever,
I want you to tell me what's going on
every single day in your office. And
then I want you to try to get a
promotion and then get transferred to
the Office of American Affairs.
And I want the names of everybody in
that office. I want to know the names of
their sources inside the United States
so the FBI can start arresting them. And
then we take it from there. And then I
can pay you in any way you want. You
know, we can open an account at the CIA
credit union, which we're very happy to
do, or we can give it to you in gold or
diamonds or Bitcoin or, you know,
however you want to handle it. We'll
give it to you.
How many of them h Okay, so I'm just
thinking like an asset they a lot of
them are probably very prideful, right?
I know a big a big vulnerability is I'm
the smartest guy in the room. I'm
>> I got passed over for promotion and I'm
going to show them.
>> So they fancy themselves as smart
people. Oh yeah. Shrewd perceptive
>> very much so.
>> And yet they didn't see this coming.
>> Yeah. So internalizing that, how many of
them want to know if it was a setup from
the start and like do they ask you for
like a face saving thing? You know what
I mean?
>> None of them want to know that that they
were duped into this or that they walked
right into it, right? So what you do in
every single meeting is you tell them
how important they are. your information
is so important, it's going directly to
the president of the United States. I
made a a guy cry once in a meeting. So,
he gave me some information. It was
good. It was the the analysts were happy
with it. It helped fill in a couple of
gaps.
He thought it was the greatest
information that's ever been passed to
the American government. So I said,
"Listen," I go, "Buddy, your information
went directly to the president of the
United States." He said, "You're kidding
me." I said, "No, directly to the
president." I said, "I wrote the report.
I sent it to the White House." He looked
at the report. What did he say? I said,
"The president read the report and he
said, "You're kidding me." He goes like
this. Oh my god.
So I I write this up. I said, "Oh, I
told him it went to the president." My
boss says, "You want to have some fun?"
He goes, "Dummy up a uh an award
certificate, put the CIA seal on it."
So, I said, "Oh, that would be fun." So,
I did a I did a in in just in word, you
know, and clip art. So, I did this, you
know, Central Intelligence Agency,
United States of America. I had the
guy's name, uh, certificate of whatever.
You put the CIA seal on it, and then I
just forged the director's name because
how's he going to know what the
director's signature looks like? So,
I go to the meeting the next month, and
I said, "I told you last month that your
information went directly to the
president of the United States." And he
said, "Yes."
He said, "I have something for you from
the director of the Central Intelligence
Agency." And I give him this phony
certificate. He looks at it and he
bursts into tears
and I said, "Congratulations, my
friend." I said, "But listen, you know,
I have to take this back and keep it in
the safe because you can't be seen with
this. You'll be killed." He goes, "Of
course, of course." I can't believe it.
Oh my god. Oh man.
I had him hooked. He was ready to name
his kids after me. That's how successful
it was. But you just play on their egos
and they eat it up. They eat it up cuz
they're all narcissists anyway. Not all,
but you know, most of them are
narcissists. They need to be stroked.
What's up, guys? Thank you so much for
taking the time to watch the interview.
If you got anything out of this video at
all, please like the video, leave me a
comment, tell me what you thought of the
video, uh, tell me who you'd like to see
on the show. I really appreciate the
support. It goes a long way on these
platforms as you guys know. Most
importantly, I have some excellent
interviews coming up in the future that
I'm really, really excited about. So,
please subscribe to the channel so you
don't miss any of them. But that's it.
Thank you for your support. I really
appreciate it and hope to see you again